<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="48824c48-20b0-417c-b591-d775c6d41b2c" scope="system" system="Specify" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1 http://rs.gbif.org/schema/eml-gbif-profile/1.0.2/eml.xsd" xml:lang="eng">
  <dataset>
    <alternateIdentifier>e9a9d022-6c43-11eb-a20c-dbb51733737e</alternateIdentifier>
    <title xml:lang="eng">NHMD Entomology Collection</title>
      <description xml:lang="" xmlns="https://eml.ecoinformatics.org/documentation-2.2.0">
       </description>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Fedor</givenName>
        <surName>Steeman</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Natural History Museum of Denmark</organizationName>
      <positionName>Data Coordinator</positionName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Universitetsparken 15</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Copenhagen</city>
        <administrativeArea>Capital Region of Denmark</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>1500</postalCode>
        <country>DK</country>
      </address>
      <phone>+45 22369539</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>fedor.steeman@snm.ku.dk</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>https://snm.ku.dk/english/</onlineUrl>
    </creator>
    <metadataProvider>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Fedor</givenName>
        <surName>Steeman</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Natural History Museum of Denmark</organizationName>
      <positionName>Data Coordinator</positionName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Universitetsparken 15</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Copenhagen</city>
        <administrativeArea>Capital Region of Denmark</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>1500</postalCode>
        <country>DK</country>
      </address>
      <phone>+45 22369539</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>fedor.steeman@snm.ku.dk</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>https://snm.ku.dk/english/</onlineUrl>
    </metadataProvider>
    <!-- <associatedParty>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Sree</givenName>
        <surName>Selvantharan</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Natural History Museum of Denmark</organizationName>
      <positionName>Project Worker</positionName>
      <electronicMailAddress>selvantharan@snm.ku.dk</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>https://samlinger.snm.ku.dk/en/dry-and-wet-collections/zoology/entomology/amber-collection/</onlineUrl>
      <role>digitization</role>
    </associatedParty> -->
    <language>eng</language>
    <abstract>
      <para xml:lang="EN">The entomological collections contain insects and other land-dwelling arthropods, such as arachnids (spiders, mites, scorpions and harvestmen) and myriapods (millipedes and centipedes).</para>
      <para xml:lang="EN">The Natural History Museum of Denmark has more than 3.5 million insects mounted on needles in the dry collection and at least a similar number of insects and land-dwelling arthropods preserved in alcohol.Around 100,000 described species are represented (of a total number of more than one million species). There are probably hundreds of as yet undescribed species in the unsorted subcollections.The collections also contain around 10,500 type specimens.</para>
      <para xml:lang="EN">Animals from all over the world are contained in the entomological collections, but some geographical areas are better represented than others. Denmark is of course well-represented, as well as the current and former members of the Danish Commonwealth (Faeroe Islands, Greenland and Iceland), for which we house the most exhaustive reference collection anywhere in the world. Especially the Danish collections contain substantial contributions from amateur collectors, who have donated their private collections.</para>
      <para xml:lang="EN">Furthermore, many sections of the collections are developed an expanded through collection trips at home and abroad. These expeditions are made regularly by the section employees, often in cooperation with international researchers. The later years have seen large collections in Denmark, Greenland, Greece, Spain, Morocco, Tunesia, Tanzania, South Africa, Thailand, India, Australia, French Guyana and southernmost South America (Argentina/Chile).</para>
      <para xml:lang="DA">De entomologiske samlinger indeholder insekter og andre landleddyr, f.eks. spindlere (edderkopper, mider, skorpioner, mejere) og myriapoder (tusindben, skolopendere).</para>
	  <para xml:lang="DA">Statens Naturhistoriske Museum har over 3,5 millioner insekter på nål i tørsamlingen og mindst lige så mange insekter og andre landleddyr i sprit. Omkring 100.000 beskrevne arter er repræsenteret (ud af et totalt antal på over en million arter). Der findes sikkert hundredevis af ubeskrevne arter i det usorterede materiale. I samlingen findes der desuden ca. 10.500 typeeksemplarer.</para>
	  <para xml:lang="DA">De entomologiske samlinger indeholder dyr fra hele verden, men nogle områder er bedre repræsenteret end andre. Det gælder naturligvis Danmark og nuværende og tidligere medlemmer af rigsfællesskabet (Færøerne, Grønland, Island), hvor vi huser de mest omfattende reference-samlinger i verden. Specielt de danske samlinger indeholder væsentlige bidrag fra amatør-samlere, der har doneret deres samlinger.</para>
	  <para xml:lang="DA">Desuden udbygges forskellige samlingsafsnit med indsamlingsrejser i ind- og udland. Disse foretages regelmæssigt af sektionens ansatte, ofte i samarbejde med udenlandske forskere. I de seneste par årtier er der foregået større indsamlinger i Danmark, Grønland, Grækenland, Spanien, Marokko, Tunesien, Tanzania, Sydafrika, Thailand, Indien, Australien, Fransk Guyana og det sydlige Sydamerika (Argentina/Chile).</para>
    </abstract>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>zoology</keyword>
      <keyword>Denmark</keyword>
      <keyword>Copenhagen</keyword>
      <keyword>Insecta</keyword>
      <keyword>entomology</keyword>
      <keyword>arachnida</keyword>
      <keyword>insects</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>n/a</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>Specimen</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>GBIF Dataset Subtype Vocabulary: http://rs.gbif.org/vocabulary/gbif/dataset_subtype.xml</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>Occurrence</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>GBIF Dataset Type Vocabulary: http://rs.gbif.org/vocabulary/gbif/dataset_type.xml</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <intellectualRights>
        <para>This work is licensed under a <ulink url="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/legalcode"><citetitle>Creative Commons Attribution (CC-BY) 4.0 License</citetitle></ulink>.</para>
      </intellectualRights>   
    <licensed>
      <licenseName>Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licenseName>
      <url>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/legalcode</url>
      <identifier>CC-BY</identifier>
    </licensed>
  <pubDate>2021-04-13</pubDate>
</dataset>
</eml:eml>