<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="48824c48-20b0-417c-b591-d775c6d41b2c" scope="system" system="Specify" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1 http://rs.gbif.org/schema/eml-gbif-profile/1.0.2/eml.xsd" xml:lang="eng">
  <dataset>
    <alternateIdentifier>b03eb233-f072-4a12-b9a6-58c2ac0fae36</alternateIdentifier>
    <title xml:lang="eng">Natural History Museum Aarhus Entomology Collection</title>
    <description />
    <!-- <associatedParty>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Kent</givenName>
        <surName>Olsen</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Natural History Museum Aarhus</organizationName>
      <positionName>Curator</positionName>
      <electronicMailAddress>kent@molslab.dk</electronicMailAddress>
	  <phone>+45 40 27 20 30</phone>
      <onlineUrl>https://www.naturhistoriskmuseum.dk/natural-history-museum-aarhus/about/employees/videnskabelige-medarbejdere/kent-olsen</onlineUrl>
      <role>curator</role>
    </associatedParty>-->
    <metadataProvider>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Hans Viborg</givenName>
        <surName>Kristensen</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Natural History Museum Aarhus</organizationName>
      <positionName>Collections manager</positionName>
      <electronicMailAddress>hans@nathist.dk</electronicMailAddress>
	  <phone>+45 40 27 13 73</phone>
      <onlineUrl>https://www.naturhistoriskmuseum.dk/om-museet/medarbejdere/videnskab/hans-viborg-kristensen</onlineUrl>
      <role>collection manager</role>
    </metadataProvider>
    <associatedParty>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Fedor Alexander</givenName>
        <surName>Steeman</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Natural History Museum of Denmark</organizationName>
      <positionName>Data Coordinator</positionName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Universitetsparken 15</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Copenhagen</city>
        <administrativeArea>Capital Region of Denmark</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>2100</postalCode>
        <country>DK</country>
      </address>
      <phone>+45 22369539</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>fedor.steeman@snm.ku.dk</electronicMailAddress>
	  <userId directory="http://orcid.org/">0000-0002-2153-8104</userId>
      <onlineUrl>https://snm.ku.dk/english/</onlineUrl>
      <role>distributor</role>
    </associatedParty>
    <language>eng</language>
    <abstract>
      <para xml:lang="EN">The dry entomological collection at the Natural History Museum Aarhus comprises at least one million specimens housed in over 7,000 insect drawers, with approximately two-thirds representing Lepidoptera. The collection has a strong focus on Danish fauna and includes specimens of nearly all Danish species of beetles, butterflies, true bugs, and hoverflies. 

Key sub-collections include Bishop Skat Hoffmeyer’s extensive collection of Danish butterflies, several other major Danish butterfly collections, numerous significant beetle collections, a comprehensive international collection of diurnal butterflies, and a large assemblage from eastern and southern Africa, primarily cicadas and grasshoppers, including several type specimens. 

The collection is an invaluable resource for researchers both nationally and internationally. It supports systematic studies, species identification, taxonomic research, biodiversity documentation, and monitoring of changes in species distributions over time.
 
Its historical depth, broad geographic coverage, and presence of type specimens make it a central reference for studies in evolution, biogeography, and the effects of climate change on insect fauna. Ongoing digitization ensures increased accessibility and fosters collaboration among researchers worldwide.</para>
      <para xml:lang="DA">Den entomologiske tørsamling på Naturhistorisk Museum Aarhus omfatter mindst én million præparater fordelt på over 7.000 insektkasser, hvoraf ca. to tredjedele er sommerfugle. Samlingen har et særligt fokus på dansk faunistik og rummer eksemplarer af næsten alle danske arter af biller, sommerfugle, tæger og svirrefluer. 

Blandt de vigtigste delsamlinger er biskop Skat Hoffmeyers store danske sommerfuglesamling, flere andre omfattende danske sommerfuglesamlinger, adskillige betydelige billesamlinger, en omfattende international samling af dagsommerfugle samt et stort materiale fra det østlige og sydlige Afrika, primært cikader og græshopper, inklusive flere typeeksemplarer. 

Samlingen er en uvurderlig ressource for forskere, både nationalt og internationalt. Den giver mulighed for systematiske studier, artsbestemmelse og taksonomiske undersøgelser, dokumentation af biodiversitet og monitorering af ændringer i udbredelse over tid.
 Den historiske dybde, det omfattende geografiske materiale og typeeksemplarer gør samlingen central for studier i evolution, biogeografi og klimaeffekter på insektfaunaen. Løbende digitalisering af samlingen øger tilgængeligheden og fremmer samarbejde mellem forskere på tværs af landegrænser.</para>
    </abstract>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>invertebrate</keyword>
      <keyword>zoology</keyword>
      <keyword>entomology</keyword>
      <keyword>Denmark</keyword>
      <keyword>Aarhus</keyword>
      <keyword>Mollusca</keyword>
      <keyword>molluscs</keyword>
      <keyword>Bivalvia</keyword>
      <keyword>bivalves</keyword>
	  <keyword>Gastropoda</keyword>
      <keyword>gastropods</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>n/a</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>Specimen</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>GBIF Dataset Subtype Vocabulary: http://rs.gbif.org/vocabulary/gbif/dataset_subtype.xml</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>Occurrence</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>GBIF Dataset Type Vocabulary: http://rs.gbif.org/vocabulary/gbif/dataset_type.xml</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <intellectualRights>
        <para>This work is licensed under a <ulink url="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/legalcode"><citetitle>Creative Commons Attribution (CC-BY) 4.0 License</citetitle></ulink>.</para>
      </intellectualRights>   
    <licensed>
      <licenseName>Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licenseName>
      <url>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/legalcode</url>
      <identifier>CC-BY</identifier>
    </licensed>
  <pubDate>2021-11-03</pubDate>
</dataset>
</eml:eml>